Guide to the Jacob Blanck Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jacob Blanck papers
1930-1947
YCAL MSS 223
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection consists primarily of corrected page proofs and a small amount of correspondence created and compiled during the publication of the fourth edition of Merle Johnson's American First Editions (1942).
Blanck, Jacob, 1906-1974
Johnson, Merle De Vore, 1874-1935 ( American first editions)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jacob Blanck, 1950.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JACOB BLANCK (1906-1974)
Jacob Blanck's career as a bibliographer and editor included positions as rare book editor of Publishers Weekly and Antiquarian Bookman, 1936-1952; bibliographer in Americana at the Library of Congress, 1939-1941; and editor of Bibliography of American Literature, 1943-1974. He also edited the third and fourth volumes of Merle Johnson's American First Editions (1936, 1942) and published four books, including two children's books. He held an honorary degree of Doctor of Letters from Brown University (1969) and a Phi Beta Kappa from Harvard University (1970). Blanck died December 25, 1974 in Jamaica Plain, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of corrected page proofs and a small amount of correspondence created and compiled during the publication of the fouth edition of Merle Johnson's American First Editions (1942), for which Blanck served as editor. The papers are arranged alphabetically by author's name.
During the editing process, Blanck sent page proofs of bibliographies to living authors, with a request for their additions and corrections. Many authors returned edited proofs along with cover letters. These instances are noted in the container list. The page proofs of other bibliographies were edited by different individuals, most commonly Carrol A. Wilson.
American literature -- Bibliography; Bibliographers; Blanck, Jacob, 1906-1974
- Page Proofs, 1930-1947
  - Aiken, Conrad, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alcott, Louisa May, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Allen, Harvey, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes correspondence from the author
  - Atherton, Gertrude Franklin Horn, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bacheller, Irving, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beebe, William, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Benet, William Rose, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Boyd, James, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bradford, Roark, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bromfield, Louis, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes correspondence with Richard J. Walsh, President of The John Day Company, Inc., Publishers
  - Bynner, Witter, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Byrne, Donn, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cabell, James Branch, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Caldwell, Erskine, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cather, Willa, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Churchill, Winston (1871-1947), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes letter from Edwin H. Carpenter, Jr. Does not include page proof
  - Cobb, Irvin S. (Irvin Shrewsbury), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Crane, Stephen, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cummings, E. E. (Edward Estlin), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Dos Passos, John, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dreiser, Theodore, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Edmonds, Walter Dumaux, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Includes correspondence with James Henle, President of The Vanguard Press
  - Ferber, Edna, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Ficke, Arthur Davison, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Fisher, Vardis, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Glasgow, Ellen Anderson Gholson, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Includes correspondence from Carroll A. Wilson
  - Hergesheimer, Joseph, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Includes correspondence from the author's secretary
  - Holmes, Oliver Wendell (1809-1894), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - James, Will, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Jeffers, Robinson, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Includes correspondence from Una Jeffers
  - Kent, Rockwell, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Lowell, James Russell, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - McFee, William, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Includes correspondence from James T. Babb
  - Morley, Christopher, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Nathan, George Jean, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Nathan, Robert, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - O'Neill, Eugene, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Roberts, Kenneth Lewis, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Saltus, Edgar, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Seton, Ernest Thompson, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Steinbeck, John, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Stockton, Frank Richard, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Stribling, T. S. (Thomas Stribling), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Tarkington, Booth, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Includes correspondence from Elizabeth Trotter
  - Van Loon, Hendrik Willem, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Wescott, Glenway, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - White, Stewart Edward, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - White, W. A., 1941 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Includes correspondence from the author but no page proofs
  - Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Includes correspondence with Carroll A. Wilson
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Miscellaneous note cards and correspondence, 1930, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 57)